Today is very special
You know, in Biel, Switzerland,
Able to make movement
In fact, there are basically five
Today we will show you one of them.
That's a museum, right?
The OMEGA Museum is here
Swatch is over there
This is the largest wooden building in Europe
This place is called Rolex Town
All Rolex products are here
Look, everyone.
That's the Rolex factory.
Friends who like mechanical watches
Have you ever seen an advertisement
A master craftsman
In a dim yellow little room
Slowly filing the gears one by one
Then make a great and expensive mechanical watch
But that was actually a lie to you.
That's all image advertising.
All current Rolex
Patek Philippe
These expensive watches from OMEGA
Actually, watches are not made like this.
Today's watches are made like this
This place is called...
Bill
Why are Swiss watches so famous?
Actually, it’s all because of Bill.
This place actually has a very large supply chain and production chain
Usually you see those videos about watches
Why do you often see
Put the parts into the watch
Then install the dial
Then install the glass
Then you finish a watch
That's because...
Everyone buys a universal movement and puts it in it
This might fool everyone.
But we as industrial people
It's easy to see
But in fact, making mechanical watches
Actually, it’s not like that
Just imagine that
People who learn to repair cars
He doesn't build cars.
A car mechanic may need to know many parts of a car.
Then there are many structures inside
But the car maker
He needs to start from scratch
Imagine how this thing would work.
It's like making a watch.
In fact, in the whole place of Biel, Switzerland
Basically a watch needs more than 60%
Swiss Made in this location
You can call it a Swiss watch
You can play on it
Made in Swiss
Otherwise you will be sued
Someone was arrested
But in fact, those image videos that everyone has seen
Or take out the movement of a mechanical watch
Disassembly and assembly
In fact, that is only 5% of the watch industry.
And the real 95% of the things are basically...
No one has ever filmed it
No one can take a picture of it
but
We can
No
We have a chance
We can shoot a little bit.
Because the industry is so huge
But today is very special
You know, in Biel, Switzerland,
Able to make movement
It's not just random mess
Then walk accurately
In fact, there are basically five
Today we will show you one of them.
From a movement
How is it designed
All the way to production
Finally completed a watch
We will show you in this episode
The secrets of Swiss watchmaking
And I tell you
The one I found today actually has sense
It feels like a Rolex.
I have sued other manufacturers.
You know, basically in Switzerland
The two major groups
One is called Rolex Group and the other is Swatch Group
He discovered that these two groups were...
no
This is getting bigger and bigger
Then if one day they are threatened
They'll be finished.
But he didn't join any gang.
I just want to find a chance to fix him.
But in the end, the repair was not successful
Why do they feel threatened?
Because they made their own movement
Slowly create from scratch
And they made more than just one movement
A movement is not so easy to make
A watch is not that easy to make.
Unless you buy someone else's movement
Then put on a face plate
Then put your own logo
That's a very well made watch.
But if you go from beginning to end
Able to make your own movement
You have to go through these steps
That is, T0, T1, T2 and then T3
Generally, everyone can see
Probably only T2
You will know why mechanical watches and self-made movements
So difficult
Before starting to make a watch
First and foremost is part design
Initially we will use 3D simulation
Not just watchmakers
And still need professional engineers
Only then can we complete the precise calculation and development of the movement
R&D is different from assembly
I emphasize again
After designing these parts
They can enter their own processing factories for production
We made a small part.
Made a gear
Then this gear is very important.
When our watch pulls out the crown
When you need to adjust the time
The gear you need in the middle when you pull it out
Then you used a machine this big.
Such a big machine
Made this gear
So we have always emphasized
This is the hardest part of making a watch.
Every part
Make every little thing yourself
It processes seven pieces at a time.
Young people don't have to wait.
I've already done it here.
here
It's done. It looks like this.
Be careful when placing it.
Because if you hit it
The accuracy is not accurate
Next, I will show you
How is a small screw made?
After this door is opened
It is a screw factory with a history of nearly 200 years.
Provides all the big brands you see
You can imagine the watch
All the screws are here.
All you see here are their products
Don't take too much at the beginning
I'll probably
I hold 6,000 in one hand and show them to everyone.
In this box
You can easily be discarded as scrap metal in Taiwan
But there are six thousand screws in it
How big is this screw?
Let me show you a bigger one first.
Did you see it?
In my hand
You'll never find it
I'm sorry
How much do I have to pay
Give me another chance
Have you seen
Here
This is a relatively large screw.
Then show you a little bit smaller.
It looks the same
Can't get confused
Did you see it here?
Your hands better be steady.
Can't find it
Don't shake your hands
Don't shake
Then I have this
Let me show you
My hands still didn't move.
Have you seen this in my hand?
This looks like residue.
Show Time
Have you seen this?
It's a slotted screw.
There are three teeth on it
One, two, three, three laps
I'll pick it up.
Then you see
If I go to work every day, I will count this
I don't even know the sky is dark.
So at this time
How can I count the six thousand in it?
I should...
I should have suppressed it.
Yes
Still here
How do we count the six thousand?
We can use this machine here.
OK
How many
So this is
Your 4 is written like this
-40 pieces
She guessed 40.
Guess how many there are?
2001 2 3
-28 pieces
Sister Ciyu, do you want to guess?
2001 2 3
-30 pieces
Wow, that's quite a difference.
I guess 15
not only
Really
Then I'll change it again
You can change one.
I want to trust someone who has been here for 25 years
So how much is it
I still think 20
It's smaller than an ant.
It is really better than ants
The ants I see at home are smaller than them.
Then it's a screw
She's finished.
-32 pieces
Wow, you're only two away.
It really is
Industry professionals
We just guessed
I still want to tell you about this
How to calculate correctly
The correct scale is this
This scale is super expensive
Then because each screw
It will first set its initial
How much does it weigh?
After the calculation
Then you pour it all in
You'll see it inside
How many in total
Otherwise you think
I'm so angry when I go to work here every day.
I calculate every day
Then take it
How much did you just calculate?
Hey, look at this
Don't think this screw
No, this candy.
This sugar bread
I've been working for a long time
Will faint
I don't know if you still remember
We were in that
During the German Machinery Exhibition
At that time, we seemed to have a picture
Just say it over there
Look at that Xingchen watch.
Then they made CNC
Then there are machines for making screws
Then I actually saw a few here.
Star Machine
But the factory is very big
It has been just in the past ten or twenty years
They've been building factories...
Because they offer all the big brands in the world
There are also small screws for medical use
I'll find a machine to show you.
How it was made
This is the material of their screws
The Swiss do it differently.
When we were watching the screwing
It's a whole bundle
Keep pumping it in like this.
But the Swiss
They like to make the material very straight
One...put it in like this
Then look carefully from this side
It will push forward section by section
Have you seen
It will move forward in sections.
Then you can see the video from our channel
You will see and feel
Why did I just talk about this silver stick?
But when you go in, it's like a golden stick
That's because there's a layer of oil inside.
Then this oil is right below
The entire processing oil and lubricating oil of the machine
Then send it in like this
First squeeze, then beat, then cut
In Germany's traditional CNC
The way they use it is like this
Previously its materials
This chuck?
Is it right to send the materials out like this?
So when you are in front of the car
You think about it
We just mentioned that if a screw is very small
Or when it is very thin
You process it here
When pressure is applied
Will it be easy to shake off?
Or it will be flexible
It won't be accurate
So it has two chucks here.
Like this
For example, when this material is delivered
I can turn around in front
I can do the machining first.
After processing
I've got the length I need.
Or in the middle
When I am in the middle of processing
I can use another chuck to hold it
Switch over here
Spin this way
Then continue processing on this side of the car.
So you will see
This is a two-head machine.
It can make a very small
Because when the material
When it is small enough
It will lose its rigidity
Then its elasticity will also change
So in this CNC processing of stainless steel
You must use oil
But the special thing is
Look over here
fire extinguisher
This is because the CNC processing
If there is oil in it, it will catch fire easily.
So if we assume today
You know Europeans
I care very much about industrial safety.
If there is a fire inside
The fire extinguisher inside it will
Then spray it directly into the entire (machine)
Then it won't let you go outside
It's all the white powder from the fire extinguisher.
So when the material is delivered
It will cut...
And what does the final product look like?
Looks like this
The original material looks like this
After processing, it looks like this
Did you see there is an S-shaped skin on my little finger?
Is it about the same size as my S leather?
Don't underestimate this.
Do you see this between my fingertips?
It's a slotted screw.
Then this is a traditional machine
You can see the material is from here
A straight line coming
It doesn't have
Like the double chuck we just looked at
Then after turning it
Look at this screw.
Fall in here
Like sand
Then you look at this brand
It’s actually a Swiss brand.
LATHES
The Swiss told me
This is what the Swiss say
It's not what I said
The Swiss say
The Japanese came here.
Then take a look and say
Oh, you make watches like this.
Then the Japanese went back and studied it
Made
You just saw the new machine.
Then they made a new machine
It defeated many Swiss and German machines.
Then something happened in the middle
It's the Quartz Crisis
Japanese and Swiss
Then they criticize each other.
Just say I'm better than you
There was once a
A local Swiss told me a story
In the past, the Japanese
They sent a very, very small steel ball
Then send it to Switzerland
Then they said, look
We can make such small steel balls
Can you
And then you know how the Swiss responded?
They're on that super small steel ball
Then a hole was drilled
Then send it back to the Japanese
So they have been
Always criticizing each other
Then until now, it is the watch war in the mall
Then I don't know if you have noticed
From just now till now
Do you feel that my hands are always like this?
Because this screw
From the time my boss gave it to me until now
It's still in my hand.
Okay, I know you can't see it either.
It doesn't matter if you can't see
Anyway, it's in my hand.
You just have to believe that it's in my hands.
This step is in the process of tabulation
This is the parts manufacturing part
The most important part of the watch is
The heart of a watch
Its hairspring
If you want to design a hairspring and a balance wheel
It's actually very difficult
Look at how complex the shape next to the balance wheel is.
In addition to a balance wheel
There are every little part in it
If you want to make your own movement today
You don't buy other people's words.
Then you need every angle
You have to draw every picture yourself
This is all at T0
You gotta get it done first.
And I tell you
This company uses the hairspring
Silicon
You know, everyone in Taiwan should know TSMC, right?
TSMC's silicon wafers
This is silicon
A person who truly makes his own movement
You must be able to make your own hairspring
My eyes are not good, I really can't see
I'm telling you, this part is cool.
You need to take this spring out.
On this chip
Is there any
This is a gossamer.
Oh X
Oh, it's over.
Now you need to buy this watch
Let me try again
Give it a try
Another watch
So this is how you all sell watches.
Asked if you want to make watches
Then take one away
And then...
Do you want to come work here?
You have very dexterous hands
great
good
Shhh
fell off
OK, now I want to buy three watches.
gossamer
The heart of a watch
It's a baby now
Now we're going to put it in
On a smaller part
Look, this is the silicon hairspring.
My armpits are all sweaty now.
Because the boss is standing behind watching
Because the boss is watching me from behind
I'm in a difficult situation now
How do I turn it back?
That’s a good question.
That’s a good question!?
Even the boss doesn't know
Back to the past, haha
Actually it fell down
Now you need to buy this watch
Then after these small parts are assembled
It's not all right once it's assembled.
Because it will make your movement
It takes three generations
Three generations of your family will be gone
So it has to be put on this instrument to measure
Did it deviate?
Then it will be placed on the machine to rotate
After the rotation you will find
Which direction and position is it leaning towards?
So don't think
Once this part is finished, it will be fine.
You'll find it's probably in the center.
When it turns, it will lean in one direction
It's going to cut it off.
It's like whether the car is balanced.
Then let it keep spinning
When you keep turning it in your hand
It just has a bias, a little bit
It will make your time inaccurate.
So there are actually some brands of mechanical watches
You can't just walk for several days.
Then the last few seconds or minutes
That is actually not done at this step.
So inside your very small mechanical watch
It is actually
You really want to make the movement yourself
When it goes very accurately
In fact, you are not even in such a small place
All need to be dealt with
Do you know why it deviates?
It's possible that I just dropped it.
Just let it go sideways
This machine is super precious.
Basically, few companies have this machine.
Because the things it knocks off are very, very thin
For more details, see here
In fact, after you take out each hairspring
Each hardness is actually different
You have to go to the machine to calibrate
This is something few people know
But in fact, in the mechanical watch
Super important things
Then the other one you know is in the mechanical watch
Important important parts
That's ruby
But ruby actually has a
I wanted to tell you all before
But there is no chance and no evidence to tell others
But today it's finally possible
that is...
In fact, many people press rubies
Just press it with your hands
Hand pressure depends on the feel of the master
You know, the feel is terrible.
There is no way to determine the data and guarantee the quality
So the real way to make ruby
It should be pressed by machine.
Then you see how he's posing now.
It has a fixture
Then take each of your rubies
How much weight should be pressed?
Then it will directly
Press up according to the needs of each one
Then its accuracy
Basically you have to control it at 1μm
Because the most difficult thing about mechanical watches is
Each of its parts is linked together
Each vibration is linked to the other
Sometimes when it goes wrong
You can't guess based on feelings.
It's every step, every stage
It all becomes digital
It all becomes quantitative
Is this ruby expensive?
Everyone used to say rubies were super expensive, right?
yes
I tell you, rubies are super cheap
Rubies are cheaper than screws, right?
-30 cents
Three cents
A three-cent coin
The screws are expensive
Screws are more expensive
The screw we just saw
Maybe more than one euro.
There are more expensive
Perrin
A Perlin inside the tourbillon
More than sixty Swiss francs
If you multiply it, it will be more than 2,000 yuan.
But I'm talking about the material cost.
It's this material
It's not included yet.
Labor is not counted
Materials
Then I can buy gems from them.
Sure, take it back.
This gem is worthless.
You take it out.
Look, there are a bunch of gems in your hand.
It's flat.
I thought it was one
Because it needs to be worn in.
It has to be pressed in.
You know every time you maintain
Are you maintaining anything?
You have to drip oil on this
Look at this ruby.
Is there any
Give this to Boss Qin.
See how much he estimates.
Please appraise
Boss Qin has 50 years of experience
I am interested in these gems.
As if motionless
I want to take this opportunity to tell you a
Cool things
Look
They are all packed in boxes like this, right?
I want to tell you one
Do you know our videos?
Sometimes, in addition to showing you the world,
There is another important thing
Industrial Management
I tell you, this is perfect for everyone.
Used by people who do warehouse management
Do you see these cute little plates on top of this?
Then there are LS, MM, TN, CB
Then it's the abbreviation of each employee
You can imagine a mechanical watch.
There are about 45 to 60 parts
This component
In fact, a component is composed of many small parts.
Balance wheel, hairspring
Are there four small screws on the balance wheel?
Then there is the central axis in the middle
Then add up all seven or eight parts.
This is called a component.
today
Super serious me
Suppose you suddenly become his employee
I took these two small parts
After I picked it up
I'm going to put my name here.
I took it away
If the next person wants to install the watch at the same time today
Or you need to install the table in other steps
Open when you can't find the parts
Why are things missing?
Who took it?
Then go find that person
You see how important management is.
You see, this is just a part.
Look, I just open it.
Is there such a thing?
Pull open
Not just here
Look here
All of this here
Look, pull it open.
All
There's something subtle about this.
It's in this line
That's five
Two Four Five Five
The green dots on it
It has been opened and used.
This one has never been opened
You can know that
I haven't opened it.
I might put 20, 30 or 50 of them in one.
So when you order something
You will know
Five here
Tuesday, Thursday, Friday, and Friday
Multiply by 50
-250
You only need to count the green stickers.
Save time
So you see
If we continue with our bad habits
Sooner or later there will be a quarrel in the company
I just can't find anything every day.
Work is inefficient
So things can’t be done well
Then everyone is unhappy
And you can't count.
Then you know the CEO here
His name is Andi
He told me
You see this QR Code above
It becomes
Every one of my
Whether I am an employee, management or anything else
I'm coming here, I'm sure
I'm going to make this part
Then I found
It seems to be out of stock
Only one left
Then I can scan the QR Code directly
I can do it for everyone
Check means
My next part
I will do it myself
No need for everyone to go to the computer
Then apply
I'm going to make this part next.
Found out that there are a few parts missing from the inventory
So I'm going to place an order now
You can see
Less
I'm going to start installing this tomorrow.
I'll place the order today
Done
So now you have some ideas about parts and components
After having the concept
We can sit on this chair.
Then we move on to the T1 step.
-T1 stage is to process all the finished parts
Install it on your movement
That is to say, the heart and skeleton of your watch
Put them all up
Some mechanical watches will become inaccurate the next day.
Some mechanical watches have been
It's not even a second off.
And T1 is the key
When assembling, you actually need
Very skilled experience and technology
in other words
-T1 is like the foundation of a house
If the foundation is unstable
There's nothing behind you.
You know it's hard enough to put the right parts together
If you find yourself in a group today
What should I do if I find that the parts don’t fit?
Then go back to step T0
Back to the computer
Redesign
Back to lathes, milling machines, CNC
Go back to T1 and do it again
But this won't happen to ordinary watch factories.
Or this wouldn't happen to a professional watch factory.
Why?
Because they will buy the movement that others have already made.
Back Group
Another one is a professional watch factory
They designed it well from the beginning.
The most difficult thing about mechanical watches
It's time to pack all your watches.
All the gaps in you
In fact, you want to control it at 3μm
If you don't control it within 3μm
Your mechanical watch must be inaccurate.
Your assembly must be bad.
Or when you are in step T0
There must be some error in your parts.
We have been talking about the unit μm for a long time on our channel.
Everyone should have an idea
You can imagine it this way
Automobile industry
It's the cylinder piston inside the engine.
That's already pretty accurate.
Its tolerance range is about 10μm
Then you understand.
-3μm
That's 1/3 of it
It's in your watch.
That's right
Actually, I should say this
Only Swiss watches are 3μm
Other countries make some cheap things
I don't know
Then, after this step is completed
You can go back to the T2 that everyone usually sees.
But in fact, we are in front of T0 and T1
In fact, we have missed a lot of steps and parts
If we film every part
We could probably do a season.
Or maybe two years.
But many concepts
It's like we used to shoot CNC machining
Lathes, milling machines
Then put it
It was originally so big
Become so small
Then let's go in and install the watch
Next, go to T2
-T2 is the most common screen.
After T1 assembly is completed
I also tested the movement and it was ok.
At this time we will enter the shelling stage
Mainly to install on the panel
second hand
Second hand, hour hand
Second hand, hour hand, minute hand
Second hand, hour hand, minute hand, put inside the case
The most important thing in this stage is
The fit between the case and the movement
In fact, this is related to its waterproofness
And the smoothness of the chain
More serious damage may result.
So although I think T0 and T1 are very powerful
-T2 seems to be nothing
But T2 is whether your watch will be affected by moisture
Is it necessary to maintain it frequently?
So to sum up
There will be talk in the watch industry
-Terms of T0 T1 T2 T3
In fact, T0 is the foundation
Be accurate and steady
-T1 is to build reinforced concrete
-T2 is to install windows, paint the exterior, and plumbing and electrical engineering
-T3 is surface modification
Wax and clean for final inspection
If all pass
Then you can live in this house.
This is basically the concept
That's it
One watch is complete
Actually, you know this video today
It is very precious.
You know we travel around the world
Every time I go to a new country or a new place
You all want to take pictures of some local factories
But the local factories
Usually people don't take pictures of others.
Especially in countries like Switzerland, Germany, Europe
Such a country
But why today we can
So many factories were photographed
With so many industrial chains and supply chains
actually...
We have one person to thank.
That person is
Founder of HORAGE
Ms. Huang
And Sister Ciyu's brand is this
HORAGE
She may be less known in Taiwan.
But she is actually quite famous in the world
Because she once made a tourbillon
Using industrial movement
Then convert to Taiwan dollars
The price is probably between 300,000 and 500,000 yuan.
Because the tourbillon
Maybe millions
But the tourbillon she made is of very good quality
You can also use it for triathlon
Then if you have been observing our
Instagram or Facebook
You will find
Sometimes when I go jogging in the morning
Especially in Switzerland
I'm wearing her tourbillon.
Then run wildly over there
Another interesting thing
You know these days
I think we've arrived in Switzerland.
I guess many Rolexes should be in stock.
Then I took her tourbillon
Then I went into the Rolex store and asked him
Do you have some Daytona
Or do you have something
Some watches that are not available in Taiwan
Then you know when I go into Rolex
How interesting is it?
Do you want me to hold your wallet?
how?
You don't want to buy?
Hey...
It's over here
I thought I was in Switzerland
That means you can buy a Rolex and it will be in stock.
Actually, it's in stock.
But the ones in stock are all that kind...
-What is the Coke circle in 2018
Like a Daytona?
No sea envoys
But one thing I want to say is this
You know, just because
He's actually quite enthusiastic.
I was asked to try on some watches.
Then what
When he took the watch from me
He is oh horage
The employees of Rolex
Then he said
Can he take a look at this watch?
Then I'll show it to him.
Then I studied it very seriously.
Then when we were chatting earlier
Because he knew I was Taiwanese.
So then he told me
Hey, this watch brand
It's also related to Taiwan.
I said, hey, you actually knew
Then the clerk was very high
I was very happy to tell you
Do you know the founder of this brand?
Are you Taiwanese too?
I want to say
Wow, this person is so famous in Switzerland
Then actually many years ago we
I just want to take pictures of mechanical watches
but...
In fact, many factories do not allow the first shot.
Then comes
Many factories do OEM for many brands
We didn't receive such a welcome when we wrote to them.
Then we came here because
I went to Switzerland on business
Then contacted Huang Ciyu
She was very welcoming.
Then she became our guarantor
She is with everyone
I've worked with her before
Then let us just say
Unbridled
Then I watched a lot of things
So this time we actually came to Switzerland
My colleagues and I
Got a huge piece of information that can be seen with your own eyes
We just discovered
There are many expensive brands.
Then in some not very...
That factory is producing
But it's a secret
It just stays in my mind.
In the future, probably only the vice president will know.
Then finally I want to thank her
It is the kindness you have shown us these days.
Then he cooked Taiwanese food for us in Switzerland
So I want to leave some space.
Let me show you some of her designs.
Cool watch
Tourbillon, everyone.
You know I like their watches.
Just look at the time, it's very clean
And then the back is beautiful.
I think the reason behind it is that
Engineers, you will think
Not exaggerated on the surface
Then turn it over
Connotation
Then and in addition
I know we have a lot of channels
Friends who like photography
Let me tell you the delicate part of this place is here.
You can see sunny and cloudy days on it.
Then it follows the camera.
How much should I adjust the ISO on a sunny day?
What should you adjust your ISO to on a cloudy day?
Then it's a comparison table
Then this is what we just formed
In fact, I think this is a
The one that is suitable for both boys and girls
Then I like it
Black and gold color combination
So she helps so much.
Do you want to buy one?
You said to open up all the relationships
Only then can we take so many photos, right?
And the one with the meteorite
meteorite
I'm telling you
You know it
What is design?
It's a meteorite falling down
Then smash it into a pit
Clam
Widmanstätten pattern
That is to say, meteorites have unique characteristics.
Then each of its lines
The lines of its cutting surface
It's all a line
Then another line
If you go diagonally
One side is 60 degrees
120 degrees on one side
That's because the meteorite is in space.
It decreases every million years
One to one hundred
So it's that extreme kind of
Slow cooling
That meteorite fell to the earth
It's probably already in space.
Wandering for 4.6 billion years
You know I heard
The person who sold the meteorite face of the watch
Taiwanese
It is to sell OMEGA to the whole world
Sell a lot to him
He is really Taiwanese.
Right, right, right
He seems to be the world's largest collector of meteorites
I saw a 600 kg one at his house.
Oh, you know him.
right
Can we go to his house next time?
(Want to see the comments below)
Then let me ask you
For example, I like tourbillon very much.
Then I can use the meteorite surface
Can I order the color I want later?
Yes, we have a tourbillon with a meteorite dial.
Tourbillon 2
She helped us get through the level like this
Yes or no...
boss
A meteorite like this
Consider it as protection money before leaving here
Otherwise, you will be beaten if you come to Bill's place next time, you know?
Will definitely be beaten
Now you need to buy a watch
Okay, that's it for this episode.
Then we again
Thank you, Sister Huang
Thank you for letting us
People in the channel
You can see a lot of
The hidden depths of mechanical watches
But if there is a chance
Of course I think everyone comes to Switzerland
Then came Bill
You may not see so many things
Because only people with some connections can get in.
So if you have the opportunity to travel around the world
Then I saw this H LOGO
Just don't forget
This is Huang Ciyu, Sister Huang
She is a Taiwanese speaker.
Taiwanese people of Swiss descent
That's it for this week's super serious video.
Goodbye everyone.
During my lunch break
Let me tell you a little story
We have told you in previous episodes
Quartz Crisis?
What it really hit hard was
The place where we are standing now
This is the area around Bill
The Quartz Crisis is not
The mineral quartz cannot be mined in Switzerland
Then came the Quartz Crisis
It was the Japanese who invented the quartz watch
Then this quartz watch
It's a complete blow.
The whole of Switzerland
Then the extent of the damage
It's true that companies are going bankrupt and closing down.
It's the kind of century-old enterprise that is directly closed down.
Then it was lost and no one learned it
Because everyone buys it.
Very cheap Japanese movement
What kind of quartz watch is it?
Say someone's name
Maybe not
yes
The instigator
All the people went to buy the Japanese
Affordable and accurate quartz watch
Because the previous mechanical watches
There's no way to be as accurate as now.
It's very inaccurate.
You need to adjust the time every day.
When I see the clock, I want to check the time.
The degree of that feeling
It's probably like...
During the Taiwan epidemic
No, I don't think it's bad enough.
That feeling is
Doesn't Taiwan have TSMC?
You think TSMC suddenly collapsed
Suddenly something was invented...
Alien Slice
Then than the wafer
And then it will be thirty times stronger
Everyone buys that
Super cheap alien slices
Then TSMC suddenly collapsed
All the 0050 you bought
Evaporated to only 1%
Do you know how tragic that would be for the entire country?
It's probably this atmosphere
This atmosphere
The Quartz Crisis was terrible
Have you ever thought that...
You know this wafer
TSMC is making that wafer
Taiwanese in Switzerland
Making watches with TSMC wafers
TSMC and Swiss watch manufacturer jointly
Look at TSMC Taiwan
This watch factory is Taiwanese
Their watches are made of that kind of...
Engineering pride, you know?
Engineer's top design
So if you are a TSMC employee
Everyone has only one TSMC version
TSMC Watch
Right?
TSMC Welfare Committee
See if you want to consider it
This collaboration doesn't happen every day.
There are Taiwanese in Swiss watch factories
Only this
I've already found it for you.
TSMC Tourbillon
silicon wafer
Swiss watches